<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' []>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-calconnect-model-vformat-00" updates="5545, 6321, 6350, 6351, 7953">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc private=""?>
<?rfc topblock="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<front>
<title abbrev="draft-calconnect-model-vformat">The Calendar and Contacts Object Model and vFormat</title>

<author initials="R. H." surname="Tse" fullname="Ronald Henry Tse">
<organization>Ribose</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Suite 1111, 1 Pedder Street</street>
<city>Central</city>
<code></code>
<country>Hong Kong</country>
<region>Hong Kong</region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>ronald.tse@ribose.com</email>
<uri>https://www.ribose.com</uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="P." surname="Tam" fullname="Peter Kwan Yu Tam">
<organization>Ribose</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Suite 1111, 1 Pedder Street</street>
<city>Central</city>
<code></code>
<country>Hong Kong</country>
<region>Hong Kong</region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>peter.tam@ribose.com</email>
<uri>https://www.ribose.com</uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="C." surname="Daboo" fullname="Cyrus Daboo">
<organization>Apple Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1 Infinite Loop</street>
<city>Cupertino</city>
<code>95014</code>
<country>USA</country>
<region>CA</region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>cyrus@daboo.name</email>
<uri>https://www.apple.com</uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="K." surname="Murchison" fullname="Kenneth Murchison">
<organization>Carnegie Mellon University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>5000 Forbes Avenue</street>
<city>Pittsburgh</city>
<code>15213</code>
<country>USA</country>
<region>PA</region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>murch@andrew.cmu.edu</email>
<uri>https://www.cmu.edu</uri>
</address>
</author>
<date year="2017" month="September" day="26"/>

<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>


<abstract>
<t>This document specifies the data format and its normalized format for
vObject, which is a generalized data format from:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>vCard version 4.0 RFC6350: the VCARD component</t>
<t>Internet Calendaring and Scheduling Core Object Specification
(iCalendar) RFC5545, the VCALENDAR, VEVENT, VJOURNAL, VFREEBUSY,
VTIMEZONE, VALARM, VTODO, STANDARD, DAYLIGHT components</t>
<t>Calendar Availability Extensions RFC7953: the VAVAILABILITY,
AVAILABLE components</t>
<t>iCalendar Patching I-Ddaboo-icalendar-vpatch: the VPATCH
component</t>
<t>Alternative formats for iCalendar: xCal RFC6321 jCal RFC7265</t>
<t>Alternative formats for vCard: xCard RFC6351, jCard RFC7095</t>
</list>
</t>
</abstract>


</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>The ubiquitous vCard <xref target="RFC6350"/> and iCalendar <xref target="RFC5545"/> standards have been
known as the &quot;vObject&quot; or &quot;VCOMPONENT&quot; family of standards,
powers digital contact exchanges, calendaring and scheduling on
over 2.5 billion devices today.
</t>
<t>Different implementations of these standards may generate different
output given identical content, causing interoperability concerns and
the general inability to determine equivalence of vObjects for integrity
concerns (Section 2.1.2 of <xref target="RFC3552"/>).
</t>
<t>A normalization procedure can be applied to vObjects (in its various
representations) to make them compatible prior to comparison, allowing
for consistent results. The result of normalization processing of a
vObject, is an equivalent vObject in vObject native representation.
</t>
<t>This document defines the general vObject data format, a normalization
form and method as a basis for vObject comparison.
</t>
<t>The normalization method has the following properties:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>stable across different implementations generating the same output
from the same input</t>
<t>compatible with alternative representation formats such as xCard
<xref target="RFC6351"/> / jCard <xref target="RFC7095"/> and xCal <xref target="RFC6321"/> / jCal <xref target="RFC7265"/></t>
<t>generates output adhering to the original vObject format allowing
interoperability with existing implementations</t>
<t>generates output compatible with protocols that utilize these
vObject, such as CardDAV <xref target="RFC6352"/> and CalDAV <xref target="RFC4791"/> systems.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>This work is produced by the CalConnect TC-VCARD committee
<xref target="CALCONNECT-VCARD"/>. The normalization form and method described in this
document is compatible with the vCard 4.0 <xref target="RFC6350"/> and iCalendar
<xref target="RFC5545"/> standards.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="conventions-used-in-this-document" title="Conventions Used in This Document">
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;,
&quot;SHALL NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;,
&quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be interpreted as
described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
</t>
<t>Notation in this document is described in ABNF <xref target="RFC5234"/> as used by
<xref target="RFC6350"/>.
</t>
<t>Definitions from <xref target="RFC6350"/> apply to this specification except when
explicitly overridden.
</t>
<t>All names of properties, property parameters, enumerated property
values, and property parameter values are case-insensitive.  However,
all property values are case-sensitive, unless otherwise stated.
</t>

<section anchor="definitions" title="Definitions">
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="vObject, VCOMPONENT">
<vspace />
a generalized format of the vCard component (VCARD) and iCalendar
(VCALENDAR) component.</t>
<t hangText="vObject Native Format">
<vspace />
the textual format representation using the &quot;BEGIN:&quot; and &quot;END:&quot;
component keywords</t>
<t hangText="inner vObject, sub-component">
<vspace />
a vObject located within a vObject.</t>
<t hangText="outer vObject, super-component">
<vspace />
a vObject that this vObject is located within.</t>
<t hangText="Client User Application (CUA)">
<vspace />
the vObject client implementation that interfaces with the user</t>
<t hangText="Calendar Date">
<vspace />
as defined in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>2.1.8</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="vobject" title="vObject Structure">
<t>Both vCard <xref target="RFC6350"/> and iCalendar <xref target="RFC5545"/> data formats belong to a
family defined as &quot;vObject&quot;. The &quot;vObject&quot; format is a generalized data
format of both vCard and iCalendar standards, and both these formats adhere
to the vObject format requirements.
</t>

<section anchor="compliant-formats" title="Compliant Formats">
<t>These formats are vObject &quot;compliant formats&quot; as they adhere to the rules of vObject:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>vCard version 4.0 <xref target="RFC6350"/>: the VCARD component</t>
<t>Internet Calendaring and Scheduling Core Object Specification
(iCalendar) <xref target="RFC5545"/>, the VCALENDAR, VEVENT, VJOURNAL, VFREEBUSY,
VTIMEZONE, VALARM, VTODO, STANDARD, DAYLIGHT components</t>
<t>Calendar Availability Extensions <xref target="RFC7953"/>: the VAVAILABILITY,
AVAILABLE components</t>
<t>iCalendar Patching <xref target="VPATCH"/>: the VPATCH component</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="elements" title="Elements">
<t>Data within a vObject is arranged through a hierarchy that is composed of
the following elements:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>component;</t>
<t>property;</t>
<t>property parameter;</t>
<t>property value;</t>
<t>property parameter value; and</t>
<t>property group.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Parsing and modification operations that work on the vObject format
SHOULD work on all its downstream formats, including
iCalendar <xref target="RFC5545"/> and vCard <xref target="RFC6350"/>.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="vobject-native-representation" title="vObject Native Representation">
<t>vObject Native Representation (the &quot;native format&quot;) is the syntax originated from the textual
representation of the iCalendar <xref target="RFC5545"/> and vCard <xref target="RFC6350"/> formats.
Its syntax is mostly tracable back to the original vCard and iCalendar
documents <xref target="vCard21"/>.
</t>
<t>This is called the &quot;native&quot; format to distinguish it from
alternative representations of vObject data,
such as those in XML or in JSON.
</t>

<section anchor="abnf-format-definition" title="ABNF Format Definition">
<t>The following ABNF notation defines the vObject Native
Representation, in accordance to <xref target="RFC5234"/>, which also defines CRLF,
WSP, DQUOTE, VCHAR, ALPHA, and DIGIT.
</t>
<t>The body of a vObject is defined by the following notation:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
vobjects = 1*vobject

vobject = "BEGIN:" comp-name CRLF
          *contentline
          *vobject
          "END:" comp-name CRLF

comp-name = name

prop-name = name

prop-values = prop-value / prop-list / prop-structured

prop-value = VALUE-CHAR

prop-list = prop-value *("," prop-value)
  ; An unordered list containing multiple property values

prop-structured = prop-value *(";" prop-value)
  ; A structured list that consist of multiple property fields
  ; for multiple property values

contentline = [group "."] prop-name params ":" prop-values CRLF
  ; Folding and unfolding procedures described in Section 3.2 of
  ; [@!RFC6350] applies:
  ;   * When parsing a content line, folded lines **MUST** first be
  ;     unfolded accordingly.
  ;   * When generating a content line, lines longer than 75
  ;     characters **SHOULD** be folded accordingly.
  ;   * When normalizing a content line, the content line **MUST**
  ;     be folded when the line is longer than 75 characters.

group = name

params = *(";" param)

param = name "=" param-value *("," param-value)
  ; Allowed parameters depend on property name.

name = 1*(ALPHA / DIGIT / "-")

param-value = *SAFE-CHAR / DQUOTE *QSAFE-CHAR DQUOTE
param-values = param-value *("," param-single-value)

NON-ASCII = UTF8-2 / UTF8-3 / UTF8-4
  ; UTF8-{2,3,4} are defined in [@RFC3629]
  ; TODO: generalize this to UTF-32

QSAFE-CHAR = WSP / "!" / %x23-7E / NON-ASCII
  ; Any character except CTLs, DQUOTE

SAFE-CHAR = WSP / "!" / %x23-39 / %x3C-7E / NON-ASCII
  ; Any character except CTLs, DQUOTE, ";", ":"

VALUE-CHAR = WSP / VCHAR / NON-ASCII
  ; Any textual character

</artwork></figure>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="normalization" title="Normalization">
<t>Normalization procedures are described within this document.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="equivalence" title="Equivalence">
<t>Two vObjects are considered identical in content if their normalized
forms are textually equivalent.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="vobject-component" title="vObject Component">
<t>A vObject is based on the representation of the &quot;component&quot; element. All
vObjects is composed of at least one component element.
</t>
<t>A component is often used to model an object in the object-oriented
sense, such as a vCard or an iCalendar object.
</t>
<t>A vObject can also contain other vObjects within and MAY contain
multiple properties.
</t>
<t>A component begins with a line that begins with the &quot;BEGIN:&quot; text
followed by the component name, and ends with a line that begins with
the &quot;END:&quot; text followed by a component name matching the component name
at the &quot;BEGIN:&quot; line.
</t>
<t>The order of components MAY represent order of the objects, which is
important for example in a VPATCH <xref target="VPATCH"/> representing the patching
order, which is not a commutative process.
</t>

<section anchor="overview" title="Overview">
<t>A component:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>begins with line of text that starts with &quot;BEGIN:&quot; following with its
component name, ending with a line break;</t>
<t>ends with a line of text that starts with &quot;END:&quot; following with its
component name (matching with the &quot;BEGIN:&quot; line), ending with a line
break;</t>
<t>can contain properties of itself and other vObject components; and</t>
<t>MUST contain a uniqueness identifier property.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The vCard <xref target="RFC6350"/> and iCalendar <xref target="RFC5545"/> data formats both
conform to the vObject format, and their syntaxes are considered to be
restricted instances of the vObject syntax.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="uniqueness-identifier" title="Uniqueness Identifying Property">
<t>As a vObject component can contain inner components, it is important
that those inner components can be distinguished from each other.
</t>
<t>A vObject component's uniqueness identifier property is a property whose
value can uniquely identify the immediate component that contains it.
</t>
<t>Every vObject component MUST contain a single, component uniqueness
identifier property.
The uniqueness identifier property can be different according to component
types, and the uniqueness scope of that property MAY be different.
At a minimum, the uniqueness identifier property value MUST be unique
within the immediate component that contains the uniqueness identifier
property.
</t>
<t>For example:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>a <spanx style="verb">VCARD</spanx> component can be distinguished among other <spanx style="verb">VCARD</spanx>
components by its <spanx style="verb">UID</spanx> property value that is globally unique;</t>
<t>a <spanx style="verb">STANDARD</spanx> component of <spanx style="verb">VTIMEZONE</spanx> can be distinguished according to
its <spanx style="verb">DTSTART</spanx> property within the <spanx style="verb">VTIMEZONE</spanx> component that contains
it.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The list of uniqueness identifier properties for every vObject component
that complies with this document can be found in the IANA registry described
in <xref target="vobject-uid-registry"/>.
</t>
<t>New vObject components defined adhering to this document MUST define a
uniqueness identifier property for that component, and it MUST be
registered in the said IANA registry.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="normalizing-a-component" title="Normalizing A Component">

<section anchor="component-name-in-uppercase" title="Component Name In Uppercase">
<t>The component name of a vObject MUST be uppercased, for both the
&quot;BEGIN:&quot; and &quot;END:&quot; content lines.
</t>
<t>Example (even though this is not technically allowed by <xref target="RFC6350"/>):
</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">BEGIN:vCard</spanx>
</t>
<t>Should be normalized to:
</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">BEGIN:VCARD</spanx>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sorted-component-properties" title="Sorted Component Properties">
<t>Properties MUST be first normalized and before sorted, meaning
that the property's values, and its parameters and its values, have been
normalized.
</t>
<t>The sorting of component properties MUST be performed according to the
following order:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>alphabetically by the property name. If a property spans multiple content
lines, the content lines MUST NOT be separated after sorting.</t>
<t>alphabetically by their normalized value.</t>
<t>alphabetically by treating its parameters as long strings</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Properties MUST be placed before inner components are listed.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sorted-inner-components" title="Sorted Inner Components">
<t>Inner components within a vObject must be placed in a sorted order.
</t>
<t>The sorting between components MUST be performed according to the
following order:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>alphabetically according to component name, such as &quot;VCALENDAR&quot;; then</t>
<t>if of the same component name, alphabetically according to the
uniqueness identifying properties (<xref target="uniqueness-identifier"/>).</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="normalized-inner-components" title="Normalized Inner Components">
<t>An inner component MUST itself be normalized, meaning that its properties
and inner components MUST be normalized.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="maintain-validity" title="Maintain Validity">
<t>Certain vObject formats places certain restrictions or requirements on
property line locations. Normalization procedures MUST NOT
affect the validity of the normalized vObject.
</t>
<t>For example, in the VCARD component <xref target="RFC6350"/>, the &quot;VERSION&quot; property
line is REQUIRED to be placed immediately below the &quot;BEGIN&quot; line.
</t>
<t>In this case, when normalizing the VCARD component, the common normalization
procedure MUST be first applied, and the &quot;VERSION&quot; property line MUST
be restored to the valid location as required by its specifications <xref target="RFC6350"/>.
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="vobject-property" title="vObject Property">
<t>Each vObject MAY contain multiple &quot;properties&quot; that represent
attributes of the vObject itself.
</t>
<t>A property can be represented by one content line (a line that ends with
a line break), but can also be &quot;folded&quot; (Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC5545"/>)
to use multiple lines.
</t>
<t>A property generally begins with the property name (e.g., &quot;TEL&quot;), followed
by a COLON delimiter and the property's value.
</t>

<section anchor="normalizing-a-vobject-property" title="Normalizing a vObject Property">

<section anchor="uppercased-property-name" title="Uppercased Property Name">
<t>The property name MUST be normalized to uppercase letters.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="normalized-values" title="Normalized Values">
<t>A normalized property MUST have normalized values.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="normalized-parameters" title="Normalized Parameters">
<t>A normalized property MUST have normalized property parameters.
</t>
<t>Property parameters within the same property MUST each be normalized, and then
sorted by parameter name alphabetically. According to the normalization procedure
of a vObject property parameter, no two parameters of the same property could
have identical names.
</t>
<t>The last property parameter of a property MUST NOT have a trailing SEMICOLON.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="wrapped-content-line" title="Wrapped Content Line">
<t>When exporting a normalized property content line, it MUST be folded at the
character limit when it exceeds 75 characters. Each folded line MUST be delimited
by the character sequence of a line break and a single white space (CRLF, SPACE (U+0020)).
This rule only applies to normalized output.
</t>
<t>For example, the original form:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
NOTE:This is a very long description on a long line that exceeds 75 characters.
</artwork></figure>
<t>When exported to normalized output MUST give out:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
NOTE:This is a very long description on a long line that exceeds 75 charac
 ters.
</artwork></figure>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="vobject-property-value" title="vObject Property Value">
<t>A vObject property MAY have one or multiple values.
The property's value(s) are defined as the content after the
property name and colon delimiter, until the end of the
unfolded content line.
</t>
<t>vObject property values are strongly typed, just like in <xref target="RFC5545"/> and
<xref target="RFC6350"/>. Basic value types accepted in vObject properties are defined in [vobject-value-types].
</t>
<t>If a property accepts multiple values, the definition of delimitation is defined in [vobject-value-types].
</t>
<t>vObject compliant formats MAY define additional value types
that are not provided in this document, and MAY require separate validation rules,
such as the &quot;RECUR&quot; property value type from iCalendar <xref target="RFC5545"/>.
</t>
<t>Each property MUST define a default value type, and MAY accept
alternative, defined, value types. If the property value type of a property value
is not the default value type, the &quot;VALUE&quot; parameter MUST be present
to specify the type of the property value.
</t>

<section anchor="normalizing-property-values" title="Normalizing Property Values">
<t>The property value generally does not require any normalization. Please consult individual
normalization instructions in each value type's definition.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="vobject-property-parameter" title="vObject Property Parameter">
<t>Each property is assigned a value, and the value is the content after
the colon delimiter until the end of the unfolded content line.
</t>
<t>A property can have attributes associated with it.  These &quot;property
parameters&quot; can contain:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>information about the property; or</t>
<t>information about the property value</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>A property MAY have multiple property parameters, for example, the
&quot;TYPE&quot; of the value or a category that applies to this value.
</t>
<t>Property parameters are optional, and exist between the property name
and the colon delimiter.
</t>
<t>Some properties allow assigning multiple property parameters in a list.
Each property parameter in a list of property parameters MUST be
separated by a SEMICOLON character.
There is no defined order among property parameters in a property parameter list.
</t>
<t>The property parameter name and the property parameter value is separated with an
equal sign (&quot;=&quot;).
</t>
<t>When there are multiple instances of a property parameter on the same property,
such as in &quot;TYPE=home;TYPE=work&quot;, it is considered equivalent to &quot;TYPE=home\,work&quot;.
</t>

<section anchor="normalizing-a-property-parameter" title="Normalizing a Property Parameter">

<section anchor="uppercased-property-parameter-names" title="Uppercased Property Parameter Names">
<t>The property parameter name MUST be normalized into uppercase letters
in form of a Unicode string (<xref target="RFC7159"/> Section 3).
</t>
<t>Property parameter names (together with their values) MUST be sorted
alphabetically.
</t>
<t>Example:
</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">TEL;VALUE=uri;type=home:tel:+1-888-888-8888</spanx>
</t>
<t>The normalized form is:
</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">TEL;TYPE="home";VALUE="uri":tel:+1-888-888-8888</spanx>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="join-identical-property-parameter-names" title="Join Identical Property Parameter Names">
<t>If a property parameter occurs more than once within a property, the
property parameter is considered to contain a list of property parameter
values joined by the parameter separator.
</t>
<t>Such instances of property parameters with identical names MUST be
joined into one instance with its value a sorted list of the property
parameter values.
</t>
<t>For example, the vCard <spanx style="verb">TEL</spanx> property's <spanx style="verb">TYPE</spanx> parameter <xref target="RFC6350"/>
describes that &quot;TYPE=home,work&quot; and &quot;TYPE=work;TYPE=home&quot; are considered
equivalent.
</t>
<t>Example:
</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">TEL;TYPE=home;Type=work;VALUE=uri:tel:+1-888-888-8888</spanx>
</t>
<t>The normalized form is:
</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">TEL;TYPE="home","work";VALUE=uri:tel:+1-888-888-8888</spanx>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="express-default-property-value-types" title="Express Default Property Value Types">
<t>In vObject formats including <xref target="RFC5545"/> and <xref target="RFC6350"/>, each property
value has a specified data type either as specified by property
definition or optionally assigned.
</t>
<t>When normalizing a property, the property data value type MUST always be
specified. If the value type is not explicitly specified, it MUST be
filled in according to the vObject format.
</t>
<t>Example:
</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">TEL:+1-888-888-8888</spanx>
</t>
<t>The normalized form is:
</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">TEL;VALUE="text":+1-888-888-8888</spanx>
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="vobject-property-parameter-value" title="vObject Property Parameter Value">
<t>A property parameter MAY contain none, one or several property
parameter values. There is generally no order enforced among the list property
parameter value list.
</t>
<t>vObject property parameter values are strongly typed, just like vObject properties, <xref target="RFC5545"/> and
<xref target="RFC6350"/>. Basic value types accepted in vObject property parameter values
are defined in [vobject-value-types].
</t>
<t>vObject compliant formats MAY define additional value types
that are not provided in this document, and MAY require separate validation rules,
such as the values accepted by the &quot;FBTYPE&quot; property parameter in iCalendar <xref target="RFC5545"/>.
</t>
<t>Each property parameter MUST define its accepted value type.
While a property MAY accept multiple alternative value types,
a property parameter value MUST only accept one value type.
</t>
<t>If a property parameter accepts multiple values, these value elements
MUST be separated by a COMMA (U+002C).
</t>
<t>Property parameter value elements that contain the COLON (U+003A),
SEMICOLON (U+003B), or COMMA (U+002C) character separators MUST be
specified as quoted-string text values.  Property parameter values
MUST NOT contain the DQUOTE (U+0022) character.  The DQUOTE character
is used as a delimiter for parameter values that contain restricted
characters or URI text.
</t>

<section anchor="normalizing-property-parameter-values" title="Normalizing Property Parameter Values">

<section anchor="sorted-parameter-values" title="Sorted Parameter Values">
<t>Property parameter values within a property parameter MUST be sorted
by value.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="wrapped-parameter-values" title="Wrapped Parameter Values">
<t>Property parameter values MUST be individually wrapped with the DQUOTE
characters. In <xref target="RFC6350"/>, the DQUOTE character is used to delimit values
within a list that contain restricted characters or URI text and is
optional.
</t>
<t>Example:
</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">TEL;TYPE=home,work;VALUE=uri:tel:+1-888-888-8888</spanx>
</t>
<t>The normalized form is:
</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">TEL;TYPE="home","work";VALUE="uri":tel:+1-888-888-8888</spanx>
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="vobject-property-group" title="vObject Property Group">
<t>Some vObjects such as the vCard <xref target="RFC6350"/> allow tagging a property with a &quot;group&quot;. A
group means that a property belongs to a certain grouping and should be displayed
together. Each property MUST only have a maximum of one group.
</t>
<t>This is useful to represent cases where a group of properties are
closely related to each other. Groups are not ordered and group names
are case-insensitive.
</t>

<section anchor="normalizing-property-groups" title="Normalizing Property Groups">

<section anchor="preserved-groups" title="Preserved Groups">
<t>Property groups MUST NOT be removed during normalization. This is contrary
to <xref target="RFC6350"/> that allows stripping off groups.
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="vobject-value-types" title="vObject Value Types">

<section anchor="meta-value-types" title="Meta Value Types">

<section anchor="list" title="LIST">
<t>Some properties and parameters allow an unordered list of values. Values in a
list of values MUST be separated by a COMMA character. There is no
significance to the order of values in a list.
</t>
<t>This construct is called the &quot;LIST&quot;. Each value in the LIST MUST have the same
value type.
</t>
<t>In vFormat syntax, an element within any LIST element MUST NOT contain
an unescaped the COMMA character to prevent breaking of the LIST syntax.
</t>
<t>Syntax
:
  When used to describe a value type, the <spanx style="verb">LIST(value-type)</spanx> function is defined as
  a list of elements separated by the COMMA character, where each of its elements
  is of value type <spanx style="verb">value-type</spanx>.
</t>
<t>Example
:
  The &quot;NICKNAME&quot; property of <xref target="RFC6350"/> defines its value to be an unordered list of TEXT.
  In vObject notation its value type is defined to be:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
LIST(TEXT)
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalizing-a-list" title="Normalizing a LIST">
<t>When normalizing a LIST, each value of it MUST be normalized,
and the values MUST be sorted alphabetically.
</t>
<t>For example, values of <xref target="RFC5545"/> RESOURCES, FREEBUSY, EXDATE, RDATE, CATEGORIES, MUST
be sorted alphabetically when normalized.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="fieldset" title="FIELDSET">
<t>Some properties and parameters require values defined in terms of multiple parts.
</t>
<t>This construct of multiple structured values is called a &quot;FIELDSET&quot;.
These structured property values MUST have their value parts separated by a
SEMICOLON character. Each value in FIELDSET MUST have the same value type as defined.
</t>
<t>In vFormat syntax, an element within any FIELDSET field MUST NOT contain
an unescaped the SEMICOLON character to prevent breaking of the FIELDSET syntax.
</t>
<t>Syntax
:
  When used to describe a value type, the <spanx style="verb">FIELDSET(field-1-value-type, ...)</spanx> function
  is defined as a structure of fields separated by the SEMICOLON character, where each
  of its fields is of value type <spanx style="verb">field-i-value-type</spanx>, where <spanx style="verb">i</spanx> represents the index
  of the specific field.
</t>
<t>Example 1
:
  The &quot;CLIENTPIDMAP&quot; property of <xref target="RFC6350"/> takes a tuple of &quot;INTEGER&quot; and &quot;URI&quot; separated
  by a SEMICOLON.
</t>
<t>The notation in vObject given for its value type would be this indicating that the first value is an INTEGER, while the latter value is a URI:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
FIELDSET(INTEGER, URI)
</artwork></figure>
<t>Example 2
:
  The &quot;N&quot; property of <xref target="RFC6350"/> defines its value of having 5 values at once, and
  each of these values are a LIST of TEXT.
</t>
<t>The notation in vObject given for its value type would be this indicating that there are 5 fields in this FIELDSET,
  and each value element of it MUST be a LIST of TEXT elements:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
FIELDSET(5\*LIST(TEXT))
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalizing-a-fieldset" title="Normalizing a FIELDSET">
<t>When normalizing a FIELDSET, each value MUST have been normalized,
but the order of FIELDSET elements MUST NOT be rearranged.
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="basic-value-types" title="Basic Value Types">

<section anchor="text" title="TEXT">
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Value Name">
<vspace />
TEXT</t>
<t hangText="Purpose
:
This value type defines values that contain free-form, human-readable text.">
<vspace />
</t>
<t hangText="Format Definition
:">
<vspace />
</t>
</list>
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
text       = *(TSAFE-CHAR / ":" / DQUOTE / ESCAPED-CHAR)
  ; Folded according to description above

ESCAPED-CHAR = ("\\" / "\;" / "\," / "\N" / "\n")
  ; \\ encodes \, \N or \n encodes newline
  ; \; encodes ;, \, encodes ,

TSAFE-CHAR = WSP / %x21 / %x23-2B / %x2D-39 / %x3C-5B /
            %x5D-7E / NON-US-ASCII
  ; Any character except CONTROLs not needed by the current
  ; character set, DQUOTE, ";", ":", "\", ","
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
  For historic reasons, the COMMA and SEMICOLON characters MUST
  be escaped with a preceding BACKSLASH character (U+005C). The historic usage
  of the &quot;text&quot; value type accepting multiple values MUST NOT be used unless
  the multiple values are provided through a LIST.
</t>
<t>An intentional line break MUST be represented by the sequence of &quot;\n&quot; or &quot;\N&quot;
  (BACKSLASH followed by a LATIN SMALL LETTER N (U+006E) or
  a LATIN CAPITAL LETTER N (U+004E)).
</t>
<t>Associated parameters
:
  * Language in which the text is represented can be controlled by
    the &quot;LANGUAGE&quot; property parameter.
</t>
<t>Example
:
  This multiple line value for the NOTE value of vCard:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
TC VCARD
The Calendaring And Scheduling Consortium
July 20, 2017
</artwork></figure>
<t>requires application of the following formatting rules:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>representing line breaks as &quot;\n&quot;</t>
<t>line folding with CRLF and the folded-line beginning with a single space</t>
<t>escaping of the COMMA character</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>and therefore SHOULD be represented as:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
NOTE:TC VCARD\nThe Calendaring And Scheduling Consortium\nJuly 20\, 2017
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-1" title="Normalization">
<t>Values of the TEXT data type MUST convert all line breaks (&quot;\n&quot; or &quot;\N&quot;) into
the character sequence &quot;\n&quot; (BACKSLASH followed by a LATIN SMALL LETTER N (U+006E)).
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="uri" title="URI">
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Value Name">
<vspace />
URI</t>
<t hangText="Purpose
:
This value type defines values that are represented by data referenced by
a uniform resource identifier (URI), the value is what the URI points to, not
the URI itself.">
<vspace />
</t>
<t hangText="Format Definition
:">
<vspace />
</t>
</list>
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
uri = &lt;As defined in Section 3 of [@!RFC3986]&gt;
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
  When a property parameter value is a URI value type, the URI MUST
  be specified as a quoted-string value.
</t>
<t>Example
:
  This value for the PHOTO property of vCard:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
PHOTO:http://www.example.com/pub/photos/jqpublic.gif

PHOTO:data:image/jpeg;base64,MIICajCCAdOgAwIBAgICBEUwDQYJKoZIhv
 AQEEBQAwdzELMAkGA1UEBhMCVVMxLDAqBgNVBAoTI05ldHNjYXBlIENvbW11bm
 ljYXRpb25zIENvcnBvcmF0aW9uMRwwGgYDVQQLExNJbmZvcm1hdGlvbiBTeXN0
 &lt;...remainder of base64-encoded data...&gt;
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-2" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="boolean" title="BOOLEAN">
<t>Value Name
:
  BOOLEAN
</t>
<t>Purpose
:
  This value type is used to identify properties that contain
  either a &quot;TRUE&quot; or &quot;FALSE&quot; Boolean value.
</t>
<t>Format Definition
:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
boolean    = "TRUE" / "FALSE"
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
</t>
<t>Parsing of &quot;TRUE&quot; and &quot;FALSE&quot; values SHOULD be case-insensitive, but
  a writer of such value MUST only output of this value type in
  uppercase.
</t>
<t>Examples
:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
TRUE
false
True
FaLSe
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-3" title="Normalization">
<t>Values of the BOOLEAN data type MUST be normalized to uppercase,
i.e., the values &quot;TRUE&quot; and &quot;FALSE&quot;.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="integer" title="INTEGER">
<t>Value Name
:
  INTEGER
  (INTEGER-32 for storing 32-bit integer, INTEGER-64 for storing 64-bit integer)
</t>
<t>Purpose
:
  Representation of a signed integer value.
</t>
<t>Format Definition
:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
integer = (["+"] / "-") 1*DIGIT
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
</t>
<t>If a preceding sign is not specified, the value is assumed positive &quot;+&quot;.
  While the format accepts the optional &quot;+&quot; PLUS sign, a writer that conforms
  to this document SHOULD not write the &quot;+&quot; sign for clarity reasons.
</t>
<t>The valid ranges for INTEGER-32 and INTEGER-64 are:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>INTEGER-32: -2147483648 (-2^31) to 2147483647 (2^31 - 1)</t>
<t>INTEGER-64: -9223372036854775807 (-2^63) to 9223372036854775808 (2^63 - 1)</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Examples
:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
  1234567890
  -1234567890
  +1234567890
  432109876
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-4" title="Normalization">
<t>A positive integer when normalized MUST not have the optional &quot;+&quot; sign.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="float" title="FLOAT">
<t>Value Name
:
  FLOAT
</t>
<t>Purpose
:
  Representation of a real-number value.
</t>
<t>Format Definition
:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
float = (["+"] / "-") 1*DIGIT ["." 1*DIGIT]
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
</t>
<t>If a preceding sign is not specified, the value is assumed positive &quot;+&quot;.
</t>
<t>Implementations MUST support a precision equal or better than that of
  the IEEE &quot;binary64&quot; format <xref target="IEEE.754.2008"/>.
</t>
<t>Scientific notation is disallowed.
</t>
<t>Examples
:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
20.30
1000000.0000001
1.333
-3.14
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-5" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
<t>Trailing zeros, such as <spanx style="verb">100.10000</spanx> MUST be kept as it indicates accuracy
of the number.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="languagetag" title="LANGUAGE-TAG">
<t>Value Name
:
  LANGUAGE-TAG
</t>
<t>Purpose
:
  Representing a language tag, as defined in <xref target="RFC5646"/>.
</t>
<t>Format Definition
:
  Defined in <xref target="RFC5646"/>.
</t>
<t>Description
:
  A single language tag
</t>
<t>Examples
:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
  de
  en-US
  sr-Cyrl
  zh-yue-HK
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-6" title="Normalization">
<t>The normalization procedure of the LANGUAGE-TAG data type follows
the procedure described in Section 2.1.1 of <xref target="RFC5646"/>.
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>language codes MUST be written in lowercase ('mn' Mongolian)</t>
<t>script codes MUST be in lowercase when the initial letter capitalized ('Cyrl' Cyrillic)</t>
<t>country codes MUST be capitalized ('MN' Mongolia)</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>As the language tag is comprised of a mixture of these components,
<xref target="RFC5646"/> provides a rule that applies this procedure across all
language tags:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>All subtags, including extension and private use subtags, MUST use lowercase letters.</t>
<t>Except: two-letter subtags that neither appear at the start of the tag
nor occur after singletons MUST be in uppercase (&quot;en-CA-x-ca&quot; or &quot;sgn-BE-FR&quot;).</t>
<t>Except: four-letter subtags that neither appear at the start of the tag
nor occur after singletons MUST be in titlecase (&quot;az-Latn-x-latn&quot;).</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="date-and-time-value-types" title="Date and Time Value Types">
<t>These date and time related value types are based on <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> and <xref target="ISO.8601.2000"/>.
</t>
<t>Multiple of such values can be specified using the comma-separated notation.
</t>

<section anchor="isodatecomplete" title="ISO-DATE-COMPLETE">
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Value Name">
<vspace />
ISO-DATE-COMPLETE</t>
<t hangText="Purpose">
<vspace />
Representation of a complete calendar date defined in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>.</t>
<t hangText="Format Definition
:">
<vspace />
</t>
</list>
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
iso-date               = iso-date-value
iso-date-value         = iso-date-fullyear iso-date-month iso-date-mday
iso-date-fullyear      = 4DIGIT
iso-date-month         = 2DIGIT   ;01-12
iso-date-mday          = 2DIGIT   ;01-28, 01-29, 01-30, 01-31
                                  ;based on month/year
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
  This value format is based on the &quot;basic format&quot; calendar date
  (specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.1.2.2 &quot;Complete representations&quot;).
</t>
<t>The value MUST be represented textually as &quot;YYYYMMDD&quot;, with its components
  &quot;YYYY&quot; a four-digit year, &quot;MM&quot; a two-digit month, and &quot;DD&quot; a two-digit day
  of the month as described in the definition.
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Example">
<vspace />
The following represents July 1, 1997:
19970701</t>
</list>
</t>

<section anchor="normalization-7" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="isodateflex" title="ISO-DATE-FLEX">
<t>Representation of a calendar date <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> that does not require
complete representation.
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Value Name">
<vspace />
ISO-DATE-FLEX</t>
<t hangText="Purpose">
<vspace />
This value type defines a calendar date format that allows entry of a
complete calendar date <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>, a reduced accuracy date <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>
and a truncated date <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>.</t>
<t hangText="Format Definition
:">
<vspace />
</t>
</list>
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
iso-date-flex   = iso-date /
                  iso-date-reduced /
                  iso-date-truncated

iso-date-reduced = iso-date-fullyear / iso-date-year-month
iso-date-year-month = iso-date-fullyear "-" iso-date-month

iso-date-truncated =  iso-date-truncated-month-day /
                      iso-date-truncated-month-only /
                      iso-date-truncated-day-only

iso-date-truncated-month-day  = "--" iso-date-month iso-date-mday
iso-date-truncated-month-only =  "--" iso-date-month
iso-date-truncated-day-only   =  "---" iso-date-mday
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
  This value format accepts:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>a complete calendar date, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.1.2.2 &quot;Complete representations&quot;,</t>
<t>a reduced accuracy calendar date, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.1.2.3 &quot;Representations with reduced accuracy&quot;, and</t>
<t>a truncated representation calendar date, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2000"/> Section 5.2.1.3 &quot;Truncated representations&quot;.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The value can be represented in these ways:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDD&quot; Complete representation basic format, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.1.2.2.</t>
<t>&quot;YYYY-MM&quot; Reduced accuracy representation, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.1.2.3 a).</t>
<t>&quot;YYYY&quot; Reduced accuracy representation, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.1.2.3 b).</t>
<t>&quot;--MMDD&quot; Truncated representation for a specific day of a month in the implied year, basic format, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2000"/> Section 5.2.1.3 d).</t>
<t>&quot;--MM&quot; Truncated representation for a specific month in the implied year, basic format, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2000"/> Section 5.2.1.3 e).</t>
<t>&quot;---DD&quot; Truncated representation for a specific day in the implied month, basic format, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2000"/> Section 5.2.1.3 f).</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Example:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
20170712
2017-07
2017
--0712
--07
---12
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-8" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="isotimecomplete" title="ISO-TIME-COMPLETE">
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Value Name">
<vspace />
ISO-TIME-COMPLETE</t>
<t hangText="Purpose">
<vspace />
Representation of a complete time of day with a UTC offset <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>.</t>
<t hangText="Format Definition
:">
<vspace />
</t>
</list>
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
iso-time = time-hour time-minute time-second
           [iso-time-utc / iso-utc-offset]

iso-time-hour    = 2DIGIT        ;00-23
iso-time-minute  = 2DIGIT        ;00-59
iso-time-second  = 2DIGIT        ;00-60
;The "60" value is used to account for positive "leap" seconds.

iso-time-utc     = "Z"
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
</t>
<t>This value format accepts a time of day value specified as:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;hhmmss&quot;, the basic format of <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.2.2.2 &quot;Complete representations&quot;.</t>
<t>&quot;hhmmssZ&quot;, the first basic format of <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.2.4 &quot;UTC of day&quot;.</t>
<t>&quot;hhmmss±hhmm&quot;, &quot;hhmmss±hh&quot;, the basic formats of <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.2.5.2 &quot;Local time and the difference from UTC&quot;</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The components mean:
  &quot;hh&quot; a two-digit, 24-hour of the day (00-23),
  &quot;mm&quot; a two-digit minute in the hour (00-59), and
  &quot;ss&quot; a two-digit second in the minute (00-60).
</t>
<t>The seconds value of 60 <spanx style="emph">MUST</spanx> only be used to account for positive &quot;leap&quot; seconds.
  Fractions of a second are not supported by this format.
</t>
<t>This value indicates &quot;local time&quot; as specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 2.1.16.
  To indicate UTC time, a &quot;Z&quot; character MUST be appended to the basic
  format as described in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.2.4 &quot;UTC of day&quot;.
  To indicate a UTC offset, the &quot;utc-offset&quot; section MUST be specified
  in accordance with <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.2.5.2.
</t>
<t>The value of &quot;hhmmssZ&quot; MUST be used instead of the equivalent &quot;hhmmss+0000&quot; or &quot;hhmmss-0000&quot;.
</t>
<t>Example:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
140000
140000Z
140000-05
140000-0500
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-9" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="isotimebasic" title="ISO-TIME-BASIC">
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Value Name">
<vspace />
ISO-TIME-BASIC</t>
<t hangText="Purpose">
<vspace />
Representation of a complete time of day disallowing a UTC offset <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>.</t>
<t hangText="Format Definition
:">
<vspace />
</t>
</list>
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
iso-time-basic = iso-time-hour iso-time-minute iso-time-second
                 [iso-time-utc]
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
  This value format is similar to &quot;TIME&quot; except it disallows the additional UTC offset,
  (the basic formats of <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.2.5.2
  &quot;Local time and the difference from UTC&quot;).
</t>
<t>This value format accepts a time of day value specified as:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;hhmmss&quot;, the basic format of <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.2.2.2 &quot;Complete representations&quot;.</t>
<t>&quot;hhmmssZ&quot;, the first basic format of <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.2.4 &quot;UTC of day&quot;.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The seconds value of 60 <spanx style="emph">MUST</spanx> only be used to account for positive &quot;leap&quot; seconds.
  Fractions of a second are not supported by this format.
</t>
<t>This value indicates &quot;local time&quot; as specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 2.1.16.
  To indicate UTC time, a &quot;Z&quot; character MUST be appended to the basic
  format as described in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.2.4 &quot;UTC of day&quot;.
</t>
<t>Example:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
232050
232050Z
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-10" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="isotimeflex" title="ISO-TIME-FLEX">
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Value Name">
<vspace />
ISO-TIME-FLEX</t>
<t hangText="Purpose">
<vspace />
This value type defines a time of day format that allows a entry of a
complete time of day <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>, a reduced accuracy date <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>
and a truncated date representation <xref target="ISO.8601.2000"/>.</t>
<t hangText="Format Definition
:">
<vspace />
</t>
</list>
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
iso-time-flex = iso-time /
                iso-time-reduced /
                iso-time-truncated

iso-time-zone = iso-time-utc / iso-time-utc-offset

iso-time-reduced =  iso-time-reduced-hour-minute /
                    iso-time-hour

iso-time-reduced-hour-minute = iso-time-hour iso-time-minute

iso-time-truncated =  iso-time-truncated-minute-second /
                      iso-time-truncated-minute-only /
                      iso-time-truncated-second-only
iso-time-truncated-minute-second = "-" iso-time-minute iso-time-second
iso-time-truncated-minute-only = "-" iso-time-minute
iso-time-truncated-second-only = "--" iso-time-second
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
  This value format accepts:
  a complete time of day, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.2.2.2 &quot;Complete representations&quot;,
  a reduced accuracy time of day, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.2.2.3 &quot;Representations with reduced accuracy&quot;,
  and a truncated representation time of day, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2000"/> Section 5.3.1.4 &quot;Truncated representations&quot;.
</t>
<t>The value can be represented in these ways:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;hhmmss&quot; Complete representation basic format, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.2.2.2.</t>
<t>&quot;hhmm&quot; Reduced accuracy representation basic format for a specific hour and minute, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.2.2.3 a).</t>
<t>&quot;hh&quot; Reduced accuracy representation basic format for a specific hour, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.2.2.3 b).</t>
<t>&quot;-mmss&quot; Truncated representation for a specific minute and second of the implied hour, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2000"/> Sections 5.3.1.4 a).</t>
<t>&quot;-mm&quot; Truncated representation for a specific minute of the implied hour, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2000"/> Sections 5.3.1.4 b).</t>
<t>&quot;--ss&quot; Truncated representation for a specific second of the implied minute, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2000"/> Sections 5.3.1.4 c).</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The seconds value of 60 <spanx style="emph">MUST</spanx> only be used to account for positive &quot;leap&quot; seconds.
  Fractions of a second are not supported by this format.
</t>
<t>This value indicates &quot;local time&quot; as specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 2.1.16.
  To indicate UTC time, a &quot;Z&quot; character MUST be appended to the basic
  format as described in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.2.4 &quot;UTC of day&quot;.
</t>
<t>This format requires the midnight hour to be represented by &quot;00&quot; (<xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>, Section 4.2.3 a)), not &quot;24&quot; (<xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>, Section 4.2.3 b)).
</t>
<t>This format supports the specificiation of UTC offsets for the
  complete representation basic format
  (defined in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>, Section 4.2.5.2 basic format),
  in the form of &quot;hhmmss±HHMM&quot;.
  &quot;HHMM&quot; is the hour and minute of UTC offset, defined in
  <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>, Section 4.2.5.1 basic format.
</t>
<t>Example:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
102200
1022
10
-2200
--00
102200Z
102200+0800
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-11" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="isoutcoffset" title="ISO-UTC-OFFSET">
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Value Name">
<vspace />
ISO-UTC-OFFSET</t>
<t hangText="Purpose">
<vspace />
Representation of a UTC offset as described in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>.</t>
<t hangText="Format Definition
:">
<vspace />
</t>
</list>
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
sign = "+" / "-"
iso-utc-offset = sign iso-time-hour [iso-time-minute]
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description:
</t>
<t>The value can be represented in two ways:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;±hhmm&quot; specified in
<xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.2.5.1 &quot;Difference between local time and UTC of day&quot;,
the first basic format.</t>
<t>&quot;±hh&quot; specified in
<xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.2.5.1 &quot;Difference between local time and UTC of day&quot;,
the second basic format.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The PLUS SIGN character MUST be specified for positive
  UTC offsets (i.e., ahead of UTC).  The HYPHEN-MINUS character MUST
  be specified for negative UTC offsets (i.e., behind of UTC).
</t>
<t>The value of &quot;-00&quot; and &quot;-0000&quot; are not allowed. The time-minute,
  if present, MUST NOT be 60; if absent, it defaults to zero.
</t>
<t>Example
:
  The following UTC offsets are given for standard time for
  New York (five hours behind UTC) and Geneva (one hour ahead of
  UTC):
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
-05
-0500
+01
+0100
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-12" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="calutcoffset" title="CAL-UTC-OFFSET">
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Value Name">
<vspace />
CAL-UTC-OFFSET</t>
<t hangText="Purpose">
<vspace />
Representation of a UTC offset as described in <xref target="RFC5545"/>.</t>
<t hangText="Format Definition
:">
<vspace />
</t>
</list>
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
cal-utc-offset = sign iso-time-hour iso-time-minute [iso-time-second]
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description:
</t>
<t>The value can be represented in two ways:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;±hhmm&quot; specified in
<xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.2.5.1 &quot;Difference between local time and UTC of day&quot;,
the first basic format.</t>
<t>&quot;±hhmmss&quot; which is unique to this value type.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The PLUS SIGN character MUST be specified for positive
  UTC offsets (i.e., ahead of UTC).  The HYPHEN-MINUS character MUST
  be specified for negative UTC offsets (i.e., behind of UTC).
</t>
<t>The value of &quot;-0000&quot; and &quot;-000000&quot; are not allowed. The time-second,
  if present, MUST NOT be 60; if absent, it defaults to zero.
</t>
<t>Example
:
  The following UTC offsets are given for standard time for
  New York (five hours behind UTC) and Geneva (one hour ahead of
  UTC):
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
-0500
-050000
+0100
+010000
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-13" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="isodatetimecomplete" title="ISO-DATE-TIME-COMPLETE">
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Value Name">
<vspace />
ISO-DATE-TIME-COMPLETE</t>
<t hangText="Purpose">
<vspace />
A complete date and time of day combination as specified in
<xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>, Section 4.3.2.</t>
<t hangText="Format Definition
:">
<vspace />
</t>
</list>
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
iso-date-time  = iso-date "T" iso-time
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
  This value format accepts a complete date and time of day representation, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.3.2 &quot;Complete representations&quot;.
</t>
<t>The value can be represented in these ways:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss&quot; 4.3.2 Complete representation basic format, first entry.</t>
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmssZ&quot; 4.3.2 Complete representation basic format, second entry.</t>
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss±hhmm&quot; 4.3.2 Complete representation basic format, third entry.</t>
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss±hh&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.3.2 Complete representation basic format, fourth entry.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Examples
:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
19850412T101530
19850412T101530Z
19850412T101530+0400
19850412T101530+04
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-14" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="isodateandortime" title="ISO-DATE-AND-OR-TIME">
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Value Name">
<vspace />
ISO-DATE-AND-OR-TIME</t>
<t hangText="Purpose">
<vspace />
Representation of a ISO-DATE-FLEX, ISO-TIME-FLEX or an ISO-DATE-TIME-FLEX value.</t>
<t hangText="Format Definition
:">
<vspace />
</t>
</list>
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
iso-date-and-or-time = iso-date-flex /
                       "T" iso-time-flex /
                       iso-date-time-flex
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
</t>
<t>This value format accepts values of ISO-DATE-FLEX, ISO-TIME-FLEX
  and ISO-DATE-TIME-FLEX.
</t>
<t>A stand-alone ISO-TIME value MUST be preceded by a &quot;T&quot;
  for unambiguous interpretation.
</t>
<t>Example
:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
19961022T140000
--1022T1400
---22T14
19850412
1985-04
1985
--0412
---12
T102200
T1022
T10
T-2200
T--00
T102200Z
T102200-0800
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-15" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="isodurationcomplete" title="ISO-DURATION-COMPLETE">
<t>Value Name
:
  ISO-DURATION-COMPLETE
</t>
<t>Purpose
:
  Representing a duration of time specified by [ISO.8604.2004] Section 4.4.3.2 complete representation basic format.
</t>
<t>Format Definition
:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">

iso-duration-sign = ["+"] / "-"
iso-duration  = ( iso-duration-sign ) "P" iso-duration-value

iso-duration-value =  iso-duration-date / iso-duration-week

iso-duration-date   = iso-duration-day "T" iso-duration-time

iso-duration-week   = 1*DIGIT "W"

iso-duration-year   = 1*DIGIT "Y"
iso-duration-month  = 1*DIGIT "M"
iso-duration-day    = 1*DIGIT "D"

iso-duration-time   = iso-duration-hour iso-duration-minute
                      iso-duration-second

iso-duration-hour   = 1*DIGIT "H"
iso-duration-minute = 1*DIGIT "M"
iso-duration-second = 1*DIGIT "S"
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
</t>
<t>The value format is based on the complete representation
  basic format specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4.3.2.
</t>
<t>It accepts the following formats (&quot;nn&quot; represents):
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;PnnW&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4.3.2, complete representation,
first basic format, for duration in weeks.</t>
<t>&quot;PnnYnnMnnDTnnHnnMnnS&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4.3.2, complete representation,
second basic format, for duration in years, months, days, hours, minutes and seconds.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>This format differs from the specification of <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4.3.2
  in the following areas:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>An optional, preceding &quot;sign&quot;, element is used to indicate positive or negative
duration. Negative durations are useful in representing reverse scheduling,
such as the time to trigger an alarm before an associated time (see <xref target="RFC5545"/>).</t>
<t>Reduced accuracy as defined in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4.3.2 is not allowed.
Omission of the number and corresponding designator of days, hours, minutes or
seconds is not allowed even if any of the expressions are zero
(<xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4.3.2 c)).</t>
<t>The duration of a week or a day depends on its position in the calendar.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>In the case of discontinuities in the time scale, such
  as the change from standard time to daylight time and back, the
  computation of the exact duration requires the subtraction or
  addition of the change of duration of the discontinuity.  Leap
  seconds MUST NOT be considered when computing an exact duration.
</t>
<t>Example
:
  A duration of 15 days, 5 hours, and 20 seconds MAY be represented as
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
P0Y0M15DT5H0M20S
</artwork></figure>
<t>A duration of 7 weeks MAY be represented as:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
P7W
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-16" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="cal-duration" title="CAL-DURATION">
<t>Value Name
:
  CAL-DURATION
</t>
<t>Purpose
:
  Representing a duration of time specified by [ISO.8604.2004] Section 4.4.3.2 complete representation basic format, simiar to ISO-DURATION, but with syntax tailored to calendaring.
</t>
<t>Format Definition
:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
cal-duration         = cal-duration-sign cal-duration-no-sign
cal-duration-sign    = (["+"] / "-")
cal-duration-no-sign = "P" cal-duration-value

cal-duration-value   = ( cal-duration-date /
                         cal-duration-time /
                         cal-duration-week )

cal-duration-date   = cal-duration-day [cal-duration-time]

cal-duration-time   = "T" ( cal-duration-hour /
                            cal-duration-minute /
                            cal-duration-second )

cal-duration-week   = 1*DIGIT "W"
cal-duration-hour   = 1*DIGIT "H" [cal-duration-minute]
cal-duration-minute = 1*DIGIT "M" [cal-duration-second]
cal-duration-second = 1*DIGIT "S"
cal-duration-day    = 1*DIGIT "D"
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
</t>
<t>The value format is similar to ISO-DURATION and based on the complete representation
  basic format specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4.3.2, but given extra flexibility
  to calendaring usage.
</t>
<t>It accepts the following formats (&quot;nn&quot; represents):
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;PnnW&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4.3.2, complete representation,
first basic format, for duration in weeks.</t>
<t>&quot;PnnDTnnHnnMnnS&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4.3.2, complete representation,
second basic format, with the omission of years and months,
for duration in days, hours, minutes and seconds.</t>
<t>&quot;PnnDTnnHnnM&quot; Reduced accuracy with omission of seconds.</t>
<t>&quot;PnnDTnnH&quot; Reduced accuracy with omission of minutes.</t>
<t>&quot;PnnD&quot; Reduced accuracy with omission of hours.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>This format differs from the specification of <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4.3.2
  in the following areas:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Years and months are not accepted in this syntax.</t>
<t>An optional, preceding &quot;sign&quot;, element is used to indicate positive or negative
duration. Negative durations are useful in representing reverse scheduling,
such as the time to trigger an alarm before an associated time (see <xref target="RFC5545"/>).</t>
<t>Reduced accuracy is allowed for in particular, the omission of the number and
designators of hours, minutes or seconds is allowed with the omission starting
from the extreme right-hand side. In the case of the omission of the time value,
the &quot;T&quot; separator MUST also be omitted. The day (&quot;D&quot;) portion MUST
always be present.</t>
<t>The duration of a week or a day depends on its position in the calendar.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>In the case of discontinuities in the time scale, such
  as the change from standard time to daylight time and back, the
  computation of the exact duration requires the subtraction or
  addition of the change of duration of the discontinuity.  Leap
  seconds MUST NOT be considered when computing an exact duration.
</t>
<t>When computing an exact duration, the greatest order time
  components MUST be added first, that is, the number of days MUST
  be added first, followed by the number of hours, number of
  minutes, and number of seconds.
</t>
<t>Example
:
  A duration of 0 days, 0 hours, and 20 seconds SHOULD be represented as
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
P0DT0H0M20S
</artwork></figure>
<t>A duration of 15 days, 5 hours, and 3 hours SHOULD be represented as
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
P15DT5H3M
</artwork></figure>
<t>A duration of 15 days, 5 hours SHOULD be represented as
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
P15DT5H
</artwork></figure>
<t>A duration of 15 days SHOULD be represented as
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
P15D
</artwork></figure>
<t>A duration of 7 weeks SHOULD be represented as:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
P7W
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-17" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="isointerval" title="ISO-INTERVAL">
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Value Name">
<vspace />
ISO-INTERVAL-COMPLETE</t>
<t hangText="Purpose
:
Representation of a time interval.">
<vspace />
</t>
<t hangText="Format Definition
:">
<vspace />
</t>
</list>
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
iso-interval     = iso-interval-explicit / iso-interval-start

iso-interval-explicit = iso-date-time "/" iso-date-time
iso-interval-start    = iso-date-time "/" iso-duration-no-sign
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
</t>
<t>This value format accepts a time interval representation, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4. &quot;Time Interval&quot;.
</t>
<t>The value can be represented by:
</t>
<t>a) a start and an end;
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss/YYYYMMDDThhmmss&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.4.4.1 Complete representation, &quot;Representations of time intervals identified by start and end&quot;, basic format, first entry. The start MUST be before the end.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>c) a start and a duration;
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss/PnnYnnMnnDTnnHnnMnnS&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.4.4.3 Complete representation, &quot;Representations of time interval identified by start and duration&quot;, first basic format. The duration component MUST be positive.</t>
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss/PnnW&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.4.4.5 Other complete representations, third item, allowing the expression &quot;PnnYnnMnnDTnnHnnMnnS&quot; to be substituted with &quot;PnnW&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.4.3.2.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>d) a duration and an end.
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;PnnYnnMnnDTnnHnnMnnS/YYYYMMDDThhmmss&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.4.4.4 Complete representation, &quot;Representations of time interval identified by duration and end&quot;, first basic format. The start of the interval can be determined by subtracting the duration component from the end of the interval.</t>
<t>&quot;PnnW/YYYYMMDDThhmmss&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.4.4.5 Other complete representations, third item, allowing the expression &quot;PnnYnnMnnDTnnHnnMnnS&quot; to be substituted with &quot;PnnW&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.4.3.2.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>In accordance with <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4.4.5:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>where representations using local time in a time point component are shown, a complete representation
of UTC (<xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.2.4) or local time and the difference from UTC
(<xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.2.5.2) MAY be substituted for local time, i.e. representations using the
expression &quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss&quot; could be substituted with any of these:
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmssZ&quot; 4.3.2 Complete representation basic format, second entry.</t>
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss±hhmm&quot; 4.3.2 Complete representation basic format, third entry.</t>
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss±hh&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.3.2 Complete representation basic format, fourth entry.</t>
</list></t>
</list>
</t>
<t>In accordance with <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4.5:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>representations for UTC included with the component preceding the solidus shall be assumed to apply to
the component following the solidus, unless a corresponding alternative is included.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Example
:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
19850412T232050/P1Y2M15DT12H30M0S
19850412T232050Z/P1Y2M15DT12H30M0S
19850412T232050Z/19850612T232050
P1Y2M15DT12H30M0S/19850412T232050
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-18" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="calinterval" title="CAL-INTERVAL">
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Value Name">
<vspace />
CAL-INTERVAL</t>
<t hangText="Purpose
:
Representation of a time interval for calendaring.">
<vspace />
</t>
<t hangText="Format Definition
:">
<vspace />
</t>
</list>
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
cal-interval     = cal-interval-explicit / cal-interval-start

cal-interval-explicit = iso-date-time-no-zone "/" iso-date-time-no-zone
cal-interval-start    = iso-date-time-no-zone "/" cal-duration-no-sign
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
</t>
<t>This value format accepts a time interval representation, specified in <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4. &quot;Time Interval&quot; tailored for calendaring purposes.
</t>
<t>The value can be represented in two ways.
</t>
<t>As an interval with start and end:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss/YYYYMMDDThhmmss&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.4.4.1 Complete representation, &quot;Representations of time intervals identified by start and end&quot;, basic format, first entry. The start MUST be before the end.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>As an interval with start and duration (positive duration only):
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss/PnnDTnnHnnMnnS&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.4.4.3 Complete representation, &quot;Representations of time interval identified by start and duration&quot;, first basic format, modified to omit the &quot;nnYnnM&quot;, which is the &quot;cal-duration&quot; period format.</t>
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss/PnnW&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.4.4.5 Other complete representations, third item, allowing the expression &quot;PnnYnnMnnDTnnHnnMnnS&quot; to be substituted with &quot;PnnW&quot; <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> 4.4.3.2.</t>
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss/PnnDTnnHnnM&quot; with the duration specified in reduced accuracy with omission of seconds as in <xref target="cal-duration"/>.</t>
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss/PnnDTnnH&quot; with the duration specified in reduced accuracy with omission of minutes as in <xref target="cal-duration"/>.</t>
<t>&quot;YYYYMMDDThhmmss/PnnD&quot; with the duration specified in reduced accuracy with omission of hours as in <xref target="cal-duration"/>.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>In accordance with <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> Section 4.4.5, representations for UTC included with the
  component preceding the solidus shall be assumed to apply to the component following the solidus,
  unless a corresponding alternative is included.
</t>
<t>Example
:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
19970101T180000Z/19970102T070000Z
19850412T232050/19850625T103000
19970101T180000Z/PT5H30M
19850412T232050/P15DT12H30M0S
19850412T232050/P00010215T123000
</artwork></figure>
<t>Both components are in UTC:
      19850412T232050Z/19850625T103000
</t>
<t>Former component in local time, latter in UTC
    19850412T232050/19850625T103000
</t>

<section anchor="normalization-19" title="Normalization">
<t>No normalization procedures are needed.
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="parameter-value-types" title="Parameter Value Types">
<t>TODO: vFormat URI in parameter values should be wrapped with DQUOTES.
</t>

<section anchor="paramvalue" title="PARAM-VALUE">
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Value Name">
<vspace />
PARAM-VALUE</t>
<t hangText="Purpose
:
This parameter value type is the basic value type for parameter values.">
<vspace />
</t>
<t hangText="Format Definition
:">
<vspace />
</t>
</list>
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center" type="abnf">
param-value   = paramtext / quoted-string

paramtext     = *SAFE-CHAR
quoted-string = DQUOTE *QSAFE-CHAR DQUOTE

QSAFE-CHAR    = WSP / %x21 / %x23-7E / NON-US-ASCII
    ; Any character except CONTROL and DQUOTE

SAFE-CHAR     = WSP / %x21 / %x23-2B / %x2D-39 / %x3C-7E
             / NON-US-ASCII
    ; Any character except CONTROL, DQUOTE, ";", ":", ","

NON-US-ASCII  = UTF8-2 / UTF8-3 / UTF8-4
     ; UTF8-2, UTF8-3, and UTF8-4 are defined in [RFC3629]

CONTROL       = %x00-08 / %x0A-1F / %x7F
     ; All the controls except HTAB
</artwork></figure>
<t>Description
:
  Values that contain the COLON, SEMICOLON, or COMMA character separators MUST
  be specified as quoted-string text values.
</t>
<t>Property parameter values that contain the DQUOTE character MUST be escaped
  and specified as quoted-string text values.
</t>
<t>Property parameter values that are not in quoted-strings are case-insensitive.
</t>
<t>An intentional line break MUST be represented by the sequence of &quot;\n&quot; or &quot;\N&quot;
  (BACKSLASH followed by a LATIN SMALL LETTER N (U+006E) or
  a LATIN CAPITAL LETTER N (U+004E)).
</t>
<t>Example
:
  The value <spanx style="verb">cid:part1.0001@example.org</spanx> in the parameter <spanx style="verb">ALTREP</spanx> within a
  <spanx style="verb">DESCRIPTION</spanx> property in iCalendar can be specified like this:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
DESCRIPTION;ALTREP="cid:part1.0001@example.org":The Fall'98 Wild
 Wizards Conference - - Las Vegas\, NV\, USA
</artwork></figure>

<section anchor="normalization-20" title="Normalization">
<t>Values of the PARAM-VALUE parameter data type MUST convert all line breaks (&quot;\n&quot; or &quot;\N&quot;) into
the character sequence &quot;\n&quot; (BACKSLASH followed by a LATIN SMALL LETTER N (U+006E)).
</t>
<t>If a value of the PARAM-VALUE type is specified as <spanx style="verb">paramtext</spanx> (i.e., not inside a quoted-string),
the value should be down-cased.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="conversion-of-property-value-types" title="Conversion Of Property Value Types">
<t>All vObject property value types are allowed in parameter values.
</t>
<t>Two primitives are defined to convert property value types into an acceptable
parameter value type within vFormat:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t><spanx style="verb">DISALLOW-DQUOTES</spanx>: converts a vObject property value type to reject DQUOTES within its value</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">WRAP-DQUOTES</spanx>: converts a vObject property value type to require outermost DQUOTES at the beginning and at the end of its value</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="normalization-method" title="Normalization Method">

<section anchor="approach" title="Approach">
<t>The goals of the normalization procedure are:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>A normalized vObject will be a valid vObject in vObject Native
Representation. Therefore the normalization procedure requires
knowledge of the source specific vObject format.</t>
<t>A normalized vObject is stable across alternative representation
formats, such as xCal and jCal of iCalendar, and xCard and jCard of
vCard. This allows comparision of vObject content regardless of the
representation format.</t>
<t>Allows comparison of equivalence of content rather than formatting.
E.g., addition of new-lines within a vCard and order of listed
properties do not affect the resulting normalized form.</t>
<t>A normalized vObject MUST maintain validity under the original
format rules, such as in the case of VCARD <xref target="RFC6350"/> and
VCALENDAR <xref target="RFC5545"/> components, the &quot;VERSION&quot; property line
MUST be located immediately after the &quot;BEGIN&quot; property line.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="steps" title="Steps">
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>Normalize the vObject
<list style="numbers">
<t>Normalize properties</t>
<t>Normalize property parameters
<list style="numbers">
<t>Normalize property parameter types</t>
<t>Normalize property parameter values</t>
<t>Sort property parameter values alphabetically.</t>
<t>Concatenate property parameter values.</t>
<t>Normalize property parameter key: cast to uppercase.</t>
<t>Concatenate string form of property parameter key, value type
and values.</t>
</list></t>
<t>Normalize property values</t>
<t>Normalize inner vObjects (sub-components)</t>
<t>Perform the same function as (1)</t>
</list></t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="functions" title="Functions">

<section anchor="sorting" title="Sorting">
<t>Sorts an list according to alphabetical order (A-Z) of its elements.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="upcase" title="Upcase">
<t>Characters in lower case SHOULD be replaced with its corresponding
upper case character. The input is expected to be in UTF-8 ASCII.
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="client-implementations-recommendations" title="Client Implementations Recommendations">
<t>A CUA SHOULD normalize the vObject upon modification of it.
</t>
<t>TODO
</t>

<section anchor="user-experience" title="User Experience">
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="carddav" title="CardDAV">

<section anchor="additional-server-semantics-for-put-copy-and-move" title="Additional Server Semantics for PUT, COPY and MOVE">
<t>This specification creates an additional precondition and postcondition
for the PUT, COPY, and MOVE methods when:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>A PUT operation requests an address object resource to be placed into
an address book collection; and</t>
<t>A COPY or MOVE operation requests an address object resource to be
placed into (or out of) an address book collection.</t>
</list>
</t>

<section anchor="provide-normalized-output" title="Provide Normalized Output">
<t>Certain servers perform silent changes or cleanups of client provided
vCard data when stored as address object resources, such as the order of
property parameters or scrubbed values.
</t>
<t>The resulting vCard data stored on the server (and when returned back to
the client) MAY end up different than that of the client without its
knowledge. It is therefore necessary for the client to be reported on
such modifications.
</t>
<t>Additional Postcondition:
</t>
<t>(CARDDAV:resource-normalized): Convert to normalized format.
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="caldav" title="CalDAV">
<t>TODO.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="alternative-vcard-representations" title="Alternative vCard representations">
<t>The normalization procedure applies to alternative vObject
representations as well, including:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>xCard <xref target="RFC6351"/></t>
<t>jCard <xref target="RFC7095"/></t>
<t>xCal <xref target="RFC6321"/></t>
<t>jCal <xref target="RFC7265"/></t>
</list>
</t>

<section anchor="xcard" title="xCard">
<t>TODO
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="jcard" title="jCard">
<t>TODO
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
<t>Security considerations around vObject formats in the following
documents MUST be adhered to:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>vCard: <xref target="RFC6350"/></t>
<t>iCalendar: <xref target="RFC5545"/>, <xref target="RFC5789"/>, <xref target="RFC4791"/></t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>New vObjects specifications produced as Standards Track RFCs MUST
adhere to the normalization format described in this document, and any
exceptions or further instructions for normalization MUST be
described.
</t>

<section anchor="vobject-component-uniqueness-properties-registration-procedure" title="vObject Component Uniqueness Properties Registration Procedure">
<t>This section defines the process to register new or modified
uniqueness properties for vObject components with IANA.
</t>
<t>The IETF will create a mailing list, vobject@ietf.org, which can be
used for public discussion of iCalendar elements proposals prior to
registration.
</t>
<t>Registration of new vObject Component Uniqueness Properties MUST
be reviewed by the designated expert and published in an RFC.
A Standards Track RFC is
REQUIRED for the registration of new vObject components
and its uniqueness property, as well as for the modification of
existing registrations.
</t>
<t>The registration procedure begins when a completed registration
template, defined in the sections below, is sent to
vobject@ietf.org and iana@iana.org.  The designated expert is
expected to tell IANA and the submitter of the registration within
two weeks whether the registration is approved, approved with minor
changes, or rejected with cause.  When a registration is rejected
with cause, it can be re-submitted if the concerns listed in the
cause are addressed.  Decisions made by the designated expert can be
appealed to the IESG Applications Area Director, then to the IESG.
They follow the normal appeals procedure for IESG decisions.
</t>

<section anchor="registration-template-for-vobject-component-uniqueness-properties" title="Registration Template for vObject Component Uniqueness Properties">
<t>A registration for a vObject Component Uniqueness Property is defined by
completing the following template.
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Component">
<vspace />
The name of the component.</t>
<t hangText="Property">
<vspace />
The property of the component that is used to uniquely identify the
component it belongs to.</t>
<t hangText="Scope">
<vspace />
The uniqueness scope of the aforementioned property.</t>
<t hangText="Reference">
<vspace />
The document that defines the component syntax and the uniqueness identifying
property. Generally, this is where the component was originally defined, but
if the uniqueness property is defined in an extension document, a reference
to the extension document SHOULD be given instead.</t>
<t hangText="Description">
<vspace />
Any special notes about the usage of the uniqueness identifying property,
how it is to be used, etc.</t>
<t hangText="Example(s)">
<vspace />
One or more examples of instances of the component need
to be specified.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="vobject-uid-registry" title="Initial vObject Component Uniqueness Identifiers Registry">
<t>The IANA created and maintains this registry for vObject Component Uniqueness
Identifiers with pointers to appropriate reference documents.
</t>
<t>The following table has been used to initialize the registry.
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Component</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Scope</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>

<c>VCALENDAR</c><c>UID</c><c>Global</c><c><xref target="RFC7986"/>, Section 5.3</c>
<c>VCARD</c><c>UID</c><c>Global</c><c><xref target="RFC6350"/>, Section 6.7.6</c>
<c>VEVENT</c><c>UID</c><c>Global</c><c><xref target="RFC5545"/>, Section 3.6.1</c>
<c>VTODO</c><c>UID</c><c>Global</c><c><xref target="RFC5545"/>, Section 3.6.2</c>
<c>VJOURNAL</c><c>UID</c><c>Global</c><c><xref target="RFC5545"/>, Section 3.6.3</c>
<c>VFREEBUSY</c><c>UID</c><c>Global</c><c><xref target="RFC5545"/>, Section 3.6.4</c>
<c>VTIMEZONE</c><c>TZID</c><c>Global</c><c><xref target="RFC5545"/>, Section 3.6.5</c>
<c>STANDARD</c><c>DTSTART</c><c>Within parent</c><c><xref target="RFC5545"/>, Section 3.6.5</c>
<c>DAYLIGHT</c><c>DTSTART</c><c>Within parent</c><c><xref target="RFC5545"/>, Section 3.6.5</c>
<c>VALARM</c><c>UID</c><c>Global</c><c><xref target="I-D.daboo-valarm-extensions"/>, Section 4</c>
<c>VAVAILABILITY</c><c>UID</c><c>Global</c><c><xref target="RFC7953"/>, Section 3.1</c>
<c>AVAILABLE</c><c>UID</c><c>Global</c><c><xref target="RFC7953"/>, Section 3.1</c>
<c>VPOLL</c><c>UID</c><c>Within parent</c><c><xref target="I-D.york-vpoll"/>, Section 4.5.1</c>
<c>VVOTER</c><c>VOTER</c><c>Within parent</c><c><xref target="I-D.york-vpoll"/>, Section 4.5.2</c>
<c>VOTE</c><c>POLL-ITEM-ID</c><c>Within parent</c><c><xref target="I-D.york-vpoll"/>, Section 4.5.3</c>
</texttable>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="normalization-examples" title="Normalization Examples">
<t>TODO!
</t>

<section anchor="vobject-native-representation-1" title="vObject Native Representation">
<t>Original:
</t>

<figure align="left"><artwork align="left">
BEGIN:VOBJECT
PROPERTY1:10
PROPERTY2:20
END:VOBJECT
</artwork></figure>
<t>Normalized:
</t>

<figure align="left"><artwork align="left">
BEGIN:VOBJECT
PROPERTY1:10
PROPERTY2:20
END:VOBJECT
</artwork></figure>
</section>

<section anchor="vcard" title="vCard">
<t>Original:
</t>

<figure align="left"><artwork align="left">
BEGIN:VCARD
VERSION:4.0
KIND:individual
FN:Martin Van Buren
N:Van Buren;Martin;;;Hon.
TEL;VALUE=uri;PREF=1;TYPE="voice,home":tel:+1-888-888-8888;ext=8888
END:VCARD
</artwork></figure>
<t>Normalized:
</t>

<figure align="left"><artwork align="left">
BEGIN:VCARD
VERSION:4.0
KIND:individual
FN:Martin Van Buren
N:Van Buren;Martin;;;Hon.
TEL;VALUE=uri;PREF=1;TYPE="voice,home":tel:+1-888-888-8888;ext=8888
END:VCARD
</artwork></figure>
</section>

<section anchor="icalendar" title="iCalendar">
</section>

<section anchor="xcard-1" title="xCard">
</section>

<section anchor="jcard-1" title="jCard">
</section>

<section anchor="xcal" title="xCal">
</section>

<section anchor="jcal" title="jCal">
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="mapping-of-data-value-types-for-existing-rfcs" title="Mapping Of Data Value Types For Existing RFCs">

<section anchor="rfc-6350" title="RFC 6350">
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>BOOLEAN</c><c>BOOLEAN</c>
<c>ISO-DATE-FLEX</c><c>DATE</c>
<c>ISO-DATE-AND-OR-TIME</c><c>DATE-AND-OR-TIME</c>
<c>ISO-DATE-TIME-FLEX</c><c>DATE-TIME</c>
<c>FLOAT</c><c>FLOAT</c>
<c>INTEGER-64</c><c>INTEGER</c>
<c>LANGUAGE-TAG</c><c>LANGUAGE-TAG</c>
<c>TEXT</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>ISO-TIME-FLEX</c><c>TIME</c>
<c>ISO-TIME-COMPLETE</c><c>TIMESTAMP</c>
<c>URI</c><c>URI</c>
<c>ISO-UTC-OFFSET</c><c>UTC-OFFSET</c>
</texttable>
</section>

<section anchor="rfc-5545" title="RFC 5545">
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>BOOLEAN</c><c>BOOLEAN</c>
<c>URI</c><c>CAL-ADDRESS</c>
<c>ISO-DATE-COMPLETE</c><c>DATE</c>
<c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c>DATE-TIME</c>
<c>CAL-DURATION</c><c>DURATION</c>
<c>FLOAT</c><c>FLOAT</c>
<c>INTEGER-32</c><c>INTEGER</c>
<c>CAL-DURATION</c><c>PERIOD</c>
<c>TEXT</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>ISO-TIME-BASIC</c><c>TIME</c>
<c>URI</c><c>URI</c>
<c>CAL-UTC-OFFSET</c><c>UTC-OFFSET</c>
<c>N/A</c><c>BINARY</c>
<c>N/A</c><c>RECUR</c>
</texttable>
<t>BINARY and RECUR do not have equivalent vObject data types.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="mapping-of-component-property-value-types-for-existing-rfcs" title="Mapping Of Component Property Value Types For Existing RFCs">

<section anchor="vcard-component-rfc-6350" title="VCARD Component (RFC 6350)">
<t>Properties with the default data type as TEXT.
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>BEGIN</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>END</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>KIND</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>XML</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>FN</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>BDAY</c><c>ISO-DATE-AND-OR-TIME</c><c>TEXT</c><c>1*date-and-or-time, 1*text</c>
<c>ANNIVERSARY</c><c>ISO-DATE-AND-OR-TIME</c><c>TEXT</c><c>1*date-and-or-time, 1*text</c>
<c>EMAIL</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT,</c>
<c>TZ</c><c>TEXT</c><c>URI, ISO-UTC-OFFSET</c><c>1*TEXT, URI, UTC-OFFSET</c>
<c>TITLE</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>ROLE</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>NOTE</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>PRODID</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>VERSION</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
</texttable>
<t>Properties with the default data type as URI.
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>TEL</c><c>URI</c><c>TEXT</c><c>1*text, URI</c>
<c>SOURCE</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>PHOTO</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>IMPP</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>GEO</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>LOGO</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>MEMBER</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>RELATED</c><c>URI</c><c>TEXT</c><c>URI, 1*text</c>
<c>UID</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI, 1*text</c>
<c>KEY</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI, 1*text</c>
<c>SOUND</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>URL</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>FBURL</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>CALADRURI</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>CALURI</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
</texttable>
<t>Properties with FIELDSET.
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>N</c><c>FIELDSET(5*LIST(TEXT))</c><c></c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>GENDER</c><c>FIELDSET(2*TEXT)</c><c></c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>ADR</c><c>FIELDSET(7*LIST(TEXT))</c><c></c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>ORG</c><c>FIELDSET(1*TEXT)</c><c></c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>CLIENTPIDMAP</c><c>FIELDSET(INTEGER-64, URI)</c><c></c><c>TEXT</c>
</texttable>
<t>Properties with LIST.
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>NICKNAME</c><c>LIST(TEXT)</c><c></c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>CATEGORIES</c><c>LIST(TEXT)</c><c></c><c>TEXT</c>
</texttable>
<t>Properties with ISO-DATE-AND-OR-TIME.
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>BDAY</c><c>ISO-DATE-AND-OR-TIME</c><c>TEXT</c><c>date-and-or-time, text</c>
<c>ANNIVERSARY</c><c>ISO-DATE-AND-OR-TIME</c><c>TEXT</c><c>date-and-or-time, text</c>
</texttable>
<t>Properties with ISO-DATE-TIME-COMPLETE.
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>REV</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-COMPLETE</c><c></c><c>timestamp</c>
</texttable>
<t>Properties with LANGUAGE-TAG.
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>LANG</c><c>LANGUAGE-TAG</c><c></c><c>language-tag</c>
</texttable>
</section>

<section anchor="vcalendar-component-rfc-5545" title="VCALENDAR Component (RFC 5545)">
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>PRODID</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>VERSION</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>CALSCALE</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>METHOD</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>IANA-REGed/X-</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
</texttable>
</section>

<section anchor="vevent-component-rfc-5545" title="VEVENT Component (RFC 5545)">
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>DTSTAMP</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME</c>
<c>UID</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>DTSTART</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c>ISO-DATE-COMPLETE</c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE</c>
<c>CLASS</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>CREATED</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME</c>
<c>DESCRIPTION</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>GEO</c><c>FIELDSET(2*FLOAT)</c><c></c><c>FLOAT &quot;;&quot; FLOAT</c>
<c>LAST-MODIFIED</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME</c>
<c>LOCATION</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>ORGANIZER</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>cal-address</c>
<c>PRIORITY</c><c>INTEGER-32</c><c></c><c>INTEGER</c>
<c>SEQUENCE</c><c>INTEGER-32</c><c></c><c>INTEGER</c>
<c>STATUS</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>SUMMARY</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>TRANSP</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>URL</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>RECURRENCE-ID</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c>ISO-DATE-COMPLETE</c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE</c>
<c>RRULE</c><c>RECUR</c><c></c><c>RECUR</c>
<c>DTEND</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c>ISO-DATE-COMPLETE</c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE</c>
<c>DURATION</c><c>DURATION</c><c></c><c>DURATION</c>
<c>ATTACH</c><c>URI</c><c>BINARY</c><c>URI, BINARY</c>
<c>ATTENDEE</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>cal-address</c>
<c>CATEGORIES</c><c>LIST(TEXT)</c><c></c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>COMMENT</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>CONTACT</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>EXDATE</c><c>LIST( ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC / ISO-DATE-COMPLETE )</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE</c>
<c>RELATED-TO</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>RESOURCES</c><c>LIST(TEXT)</c><c></c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>RDATE</c><c>LIST( ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC / ISO-DATE-COMPLETE / CAL-INTERVAL)</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE, PERIOD</c>
<c>IANA-REGed/X-</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
</texttable>
<t>RRULE uses the RECUR data value type, which is a special construct
defined in <xref target="RFC5545"/> with no equivalent in this document.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="vtodo-component-rfc-5545" title="VTODO Component (RFC 5545)">
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>DTSTAMP</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME</c>
<c>UID</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>CLASS</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>CREATED</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME</c>
<c>COMPLETED</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME</c>
<c>DESCRIPTION</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>DTSTART</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c>ISO-DATE-COMPLETE</c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE</c>
<c>GEO</c><c>FIELDSET(2*FLOAT)</c><c></c><c>FLOAT &quot;;&quot; FLOAT</c>
<c>LAST-MODIFIED</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME</c>
<c>LOCATION</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>ORGANIZER</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>cal-address</c>
<c>PRIORITY</c><c>INTEGER-32</c><c></c><c>INTEGER</c>
<c>SEQUENCE</c><c>INTEGER-32</c><c></c><c>INTEGER</c>
<c>STATUS</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>SUMMARY</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>URL</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>RRULE</c><c>RECUR</c><c></c><c>RECUR</c>
<c>DUE</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c>ISO-DATE-COMPLETE</c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE</c>
<c>DURATION</c><c>DURATION</c><c></c><c>DURATION</c>
<c>ATTACH</c><c>URI</c><c>BINARY</c><c>URI, BINARY</c>
<c>ATTENDEE</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>cal-address</c>
<c>CATEGORIES</c><c>LIST(TEXT)</c><c></c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>COMMENT</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>CONTACT</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>EXDATE</c><c>LIST( ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC / ISO-DATE-COMPLETE )</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE</c>
<c>REQUEST-STATUS</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>RELATED-TO</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>RESOURCES</c><c>LIST(TEXT)</c><c></c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>RDATE</c><c>LIST( ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC / ISO-DATE-COMPLETE / CAL-INTERVAL)</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE, PERIOD</c>
<c>IANA-REGed/X-</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
</texttable>
<t>RRULE uses the RECUR data value type, which is a special construct
defined in <xref target="RFC5545"/> with no equivalent in this document.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="vjournal-component-rfc-5545" title="VJOURNAL Component (RFC 5545)">
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>DTSTAMP</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME</c>
<c>UID</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>CLASS</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>CREATED</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME</c>
<c>DTSTART</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c>ISO-DATE-COMPLETE</c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE</c>
<c>LAST-MODIFIED</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME</c>
<c>ORGANIZER</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>cal-address</c>
<c>SEQUENCE</c><c>INTEGER-32</c><c></c><c>INTEGER</c>
<c>STATUS</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>SUMMARY</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>URL</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>RRULE</c><c>RECUR</c><c></c><c>RECUR</c>
<c>ATTACH</c><c>URI</c><c>BINARY</c><c>URI, BINARY</c>
<c>ATTENDEE</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>cal-address</c>
<c>CATEGORIES</c><c>LIST(TEXT)</c><c></c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>COMMENT</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>CONTACT</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>DESCRIPTION</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>EXDATE</c><c>LIST( ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC / ISO-DATE-COMPLETE )</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE</c>
<c>RELATED-TO</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>RDATE</c><c>LIST( ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC / ISO-DATE-COMPLETE / CAL-INTERVAL)</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE, PERIOD</c>
<c>REQUEST-STATUS</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>IANA-REGed/X-</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
</texttable>
<t>RRULE uses the RECUR data value type, which is a special construct
defined in <xref target="RFC5545"/> with no equivalent in this document.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="vfreebusy-component-rfc-5545" title="VFREEBUSY Component (RFC 5545)">
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>DTSTAMP</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME</c>
<c>UID</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>CONTACT</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>DTSTART</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c>ISO-DATE-COMPLETE</c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE</c>
<c>DTEND</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c>ISO-DATE-COMPLETE</c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE</c>
<c>ORGANIZER</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>cal-address</c>
<c>URL</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>ATTENDEE</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>cal-address</c>
<c>COMMENT</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>FREEBUSY</c><c>LIST(CAL-INTERVAL)</c><c></c><c>LIST(PERIOD)</c>
<c>REQUEST-STATUS</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>IANA-REGed/X-</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
</texttable>
</section>

<section anchor="vtimezone-component-rfc-5545" title="VTIMEZONE Component (RFC 5545)">
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>TZID</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>LAST-MODIFIED</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME</c>
<c>TZURL</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>URI</c>
<c>IANA-REGed/X-</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
</texttable>
</section>

<section anchor="standard--daylight-components-rfc-5545" title="STANDARD / DAYLIGHT Components (RFC 5545)">
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>DTSTART</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c>ISO-DATE-COMPLETE</c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE</c>
<c>TZOFFSETFROM</c><c>CAL-UTC-OFFSET</c><c></c><c>UTC-OFFSET</c>
<c>TZOFFSETTO</c><c>CAL-UTC-OFFSET</c><c></c><c>UTC-OFFSET</c>
<c>RRULE</c><c>RECUR</c><c></c><c>RECUR</c>
<c>COMMENT</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>RDATE</c><c>LIST( ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC / ISO-DATE-COMPLETE / CAL-INTERVAL)</c><c></c><c>DATE-TIME, DATE, PERIOD</c>
<c>TZNAME</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>IANA-REGed/X-</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
</texttable>
<t>RRULE uses the RECUR data value type, which is a special construct
defined in <xref target="RFC5545"/> with no equivalent in this document.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="valarm-component-rfc-5545" title="VALARM Component (RFC 5545)">
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default Data Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Alt. Data Types</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Original Data Type</ttcol>

<c>ACTION</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>DESCRIPTION</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>SUMMARY</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
<c>TRIGGER</c><c>DURATION</c><c>ISO-DATE-TIME-BASIC</c><c>DURATION, DATE-TIME</c>
<c>DURATION</c><c>DURATION</c><c></c><c>DURATION</c>
<c>REPEAT</c><c>INTEGER-32</c><c></c><c>INTEGER</c>
<c>ATTACH</c><c>URI</c><c>BINARY</c><c>URI, BINARY</c>
<c>ATTENDEE</c><c>URI</c><c></c><c>cal-address</c>
<c>IANA-REGed/X-</c><c>TEXT</c><c></c><c>1*TEXT</c>
</texttable>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="mapping-of-parameter-value-types-for-existing-rfcs" title="Mapping Of Parameter Value Types For Existing RFCs">

<section anchor="rfc-6350-1" title="RFC 6350">
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Parameter</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Data Type</ttcol>

<c>LANGUAGE</c><c>LANGUAGE-TAG</c>
<c>VALUE</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>PREF</c><c>INTEGER-64</c>
<c>ALTID</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>PID</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>TYPE</c><c>LIST(TEXT)</c>
<c>MEDIATYPE</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>CALSCALE</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>SORT-AS</c><c>LIST(TEXT)</c>
<c>GEO</c><c>URI</c>
<c>TZ</c><c>TEXT</c>
</texttable>
</section>

<section anchor="rfc-5545-1" title="RFC 5545">
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Parameter</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Data Type</ttcol>

<c>ALTREP</c><c>URI</c>
<c>CN</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>CUTYPE</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>DELEGATED-FROM</c><c>URI</c>
<c>DELEGATED-TO</c><c>URI</c>
<c>DIR</c><c>URI</c>
<c>ENCODING</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>FMTTYPE</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>FBTYPE</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>LANGUAGE</c><c>LANGUAGE-TAG</c>
<c>MEMBER</c><c>LIST(URI)</c>
<c>PARTSTAT</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>RANGE</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>RELATED</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>RELTYPE</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>ROLE</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>RSVP</c><c>BOOLEAN</c>
<c>SENT-BY</c><c>URI</c>
<c>TZID</c><c>TEXT</c>
<c>VALUE</c><c>TEXT</c>
</texttable>
</section>
</section>

</middle>
<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<reference anchor='ISO.8601.2000' target='https://www.iso.org/standard/26780.html'>
  <front>
    <title>ISO 8601:2000, Data elements and interchange formats -- Information interchange -- Representation of dates and times</title>
    <author>
      <organization>ISO/IEC</organization>
      <address>
        <uri>http://www.iso.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month='December' year='2000'/>
    <abstract><t></t></abstract>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor='ISO.8601.2004' target='https://www.iso.org/standard/40874.html'>
  <front>
    <title>ISO 8601:2004, Data elements and interchange formats -- Information interchange -- Representation of dates and times</title>
    <author>
      <organization>ISO/IEC</organization>
      <address>
        <uri>http://www.iso.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month='December' year='2004'/>
    <abstract><t></t></abstract>
  </front>
</reference>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4791.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5545.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5646.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5789.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6350.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6352.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7159.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7953.xml"?>
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
<reference anchor='CALCONNECT-VCARD' target='http://calconnect.org/about/technical-committees/vcard-technical-committee'>
  <front>
    <title>CalConnect VCARD Technical Committee</title>
    <author>
      <organization>The Calendaring and Scheduling Consortium</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
         <street>4390 Chaffin Lane</street>
         <city>McKinleyville</city>
         <region>CA</region>
         <code>95519-8028</code>
         <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>contact@calconnect.org</email>
        <uri>https://www.calconnect.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month='March' year='2017'/>
  </front>
</reference>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.daboo-valarm-extensions.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.york-vpoll.xml"?>
<reference anchor='IEEE.754.2008' target='https://doi.org/10.1109/IEEESTD.2008.4610935'>
  <front>
    <title>IEEE Standard 754, Standard for Binary Floating-Point Arithmetic</title>
    <author>
      <organization>Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers</organization>
      <address>
        <uri>http://www.ieee.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month='August' year='2008'/>
    <abstract><t></t></abstract>
  </front>
</reference>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6321.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6351.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7095.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7265.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7986.xml"?>
<reference anchor='VPATCH'>
  <front>
    <title>The iCalendar VPATCH Component (draft)</title>
    <author initials="C." surname="Daboo" fullname="Cyrus Daboo">
      <organization>Apple Inc.</organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="K." surname="Murchison" fullname="Ken Murchison">
      <organization>Carnegie Mellon University</organization>
    </author>
    <date month='10' day='28' year='2016'/>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor='vCard21'>
  <front>
    <title>vCard - The Electronic Business Card Version 2.1</title>
    <author>
      <organization>Internet Mail Consortium</organization>
    </author>
    <date month='09' year='1996'/>
  </front>
</reference>
</references>

<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
<t>The authors wish to thank their families and the following parties who
helped this materialize and for their support of a better and
vObject-enabled world:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t><eref target="mailto:marten@dmfs.org">Marten Gajda</eref></t>
<t>the CalConnect TC-VCARD committee</t>
<t>members and the Board of Directors of CalConnect</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>This specification was developed by the CalConnect TC-VCARD committee.
</t>
</section>

</back>
</rfc>
